<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vnrighteous iudge, or, Iudex cretensis, the iudge of Crete a sermon preached within the iurisdiction of the arch-deaconry of Norwich, at a generall court, in April last past, 16. 1621 / by Mr. Yonger of South-Walsham.</title>
            <author>Yonger, William, b. 1572 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26098.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22634223</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22634223</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1056:12 or 1760:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vnrighteous iudge, or, Iudex cretensis, the iudge of Crete a sermon preached within the iurisdiction of the arch-deaconry of Norwich, at a generall court, in April last past, 16. 1621 / by Mr. Yonger of South-Walsham.</title>
                  <author>Yonger, William, b. 1572 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld, for Henry Fetherstone, and are to be solde by Christopher Puntar of Norwich booke-seller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The vnrighteous iudge: or, The iudge of Crete.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 26098 at reel 1056:12.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the British Library (reel 1056) and Harvard University. Library (reel 1760).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XVIII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fear of God --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22662:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22662:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNRIGHTEOVS IVDGE: OR, <hi>JVDEX CRETENSIS,</hi> The Iudge of CRETE. A SERMON PREACHED within the Iuriſdiction of the Arch-Deaconry of <hi>Norwich,</hi> at a Generall Court, in <hi>April</hi> laſt paſt, 16. 1621. By M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. YONGER of <hi>South-Walſham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Dat Roſa mel Apibus, quâſugit Aranea virus.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by G. ELD, for <hi>Henry Fetherſtone,</hi> and are to be ſolde by <hi>Chriſtofer Puntar</hi> of <hi>Norwich</hi> Booke-ſeller. 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22662:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22662:2"/>
            <head>The Vnrighteous IVDGE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVKE 18.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There was a Iudge in a certaine Citie, who feared not God, nor regardsd man.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Muſt open my mouth in a Parable, and declare ſome hard ſentences; that it is a Parable the Euangeliſt makes it plaine: (Alas! (if it be a true ſtory) that any Iudge ſhould be ſo wicked.) <hi>Chriſt ſpake alſo a Parable vnto them,</hi> that vnder the figure and ſimilitude thereof, we ſhould be ſtirred vp, <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to pray, and not to waxe faint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubiect or matter of the Parable runnes vpon a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of a Iudge and a Widow. For the widow at this time I meddle not with, ſhe comes not within the verge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of my Text: All my buſineſſe muſt lie about the Iudge. And I find him here ſo ill, as I thinke I could not haue ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon a worſe: for, <hi>he feared not God.</hi> And though he had neuer beene ſo graceleſſe and debauſht, that neither he had cared for God, nor God for him; yet (me thinks) he might haue had the good word and applauſe of men, or giuen them ſome eſteeme. No, the Text ſayth, hee was at a point with them too, for as he <hi>feared</hi> not the one, ſo he reſpected not the other, <hi>he regarded not man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this while you ſee he is a very ill Iudge, and I will promiſe ere wee part, he ſhall fare as ill at my hands. But I will gather and girt vp my ſelfe more cloſely to the words.</p>
            <p>The parts of the Text are apparantly two.
<note place="margin">Parts,</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. You ſee the <hi>Perſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Qualities</hi> of the <hi>Perſon.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:22662:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>Perſon</hi> for his Office is a Iudge.
<note place="margin">Gen. 31.11.</note> And he comes here attended, as Iudges vſe to doe. Yea, <hi>Behold a company cometh:</hi> for he is waited vpon in the text, with many followers, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, accoutrements, circumſtances if you will. 1. Of the <hi>Time,</hi> which is not of the preſent, but of that which is paſt. For Chriſt doth not ſay, There is: no, it ſeemes they had a change, and their hap was better: great pitty had it beene, ſo vile a man ſhould haue holden his place ſtill; it is the liklieſt he was put off; he was <hi>Iudex quondam;</hi> wee ſee what Chriſt here ſaith, <hi>erat; non eſt,</hi> there is not; but, <hi>there was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Greeke, is attended with the Article <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as with a little Page, and ſo it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Iudge:</hi> He was but ſome one; and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>In a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine City.</hi> He was ſingular from all example, both for <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>place. A certaine Iudge, in a certaine City.</hi> Hee was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A certaine Iudge,</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, it is not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary for men to be ſo wicked, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in a certaine City,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, it is not ordinary in Cities to haue ſuch Iudges.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is worth the noting, that the Article is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he was but a <hi>certaine Iudge;</hi> He was not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the onely <hi>Iudge,</hi> but a Iudge of ſome ſubordinate and inferiour place; and whether he were a Temporall Iudge or an Eccleſiaſticall, we cannot tell, they had both in former times, as we haue now. And we know the widowes cauſe comes as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, as before the Temporall.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Obſerue the <hi>place,</hi> hee was in a <hi>City.</hi> But Chriſt doth not ſay in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> No! that was the <hi>City of God,</hi> and it is likelieſt there were Iudges that <hi>feared God:</hi> Nor in <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> yet there had beene Iudges wicked inough. Nay I doe not thinke, he was in any one <hi>City</hi> in all Iſrael or Iudah, for <hi>Notus in Iudea Deus; God is well knowne in Iewry, His Name is great in Iſrael.</hi> It might be therefore ſome <hi>certaine City</hi> amongſt the Gentiles. And we may as well ſuppoſe it, to be ſome one <hi>City</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Creet,</hi> as any other where: The Apoſtle tells vs, from their owne Poets, the Cretians
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22662:3"/>are <hi>euill beaſts,</hi> and if there were a fowler beaſt then this, I haue much maruayle. I pray ſee his qualities; they are two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Ex parte Dei, He feared not God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Ex parte hominis, He regarded not Man.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>It ſeemes he had neither <hi>Religion,</hi> nor good <hi>manners.</hi> For firſt, where as in each of theſe qualities, as about the skirt of <hi>Aarons</hi> robe, there was a <hi>Bell</hi> and a <hi>Pomegranate,</hi> a <hi>Bell</hi> and a <hi>Pomegranate, Exod.</hi> 39.15. So here a quality and the obiect, a quality and the obiect; as in the firſt member <hi>ex parte Dei,</hi> the quality is <hi>feare,</hi> and the proper obect is <hi>God.</hi> And in the ſecond member <hi>ex parte hominis,</hi> the quality is <hi>regard,</hi> and the proper obiect is <hi>Man:</hi> and theſe are poſitiuely, and real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in euery good man; yet here is a nullity, a priuation of them, as appeares by the two <hi>negatiues,</hi> he feared <hi>not</hi> God. hee regarded <hi>not</hi> man; hee was wanting in the one, hee was wanting in the other.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hee was <hi>totus deficiens,</hi> wholy wanting; for whereas there are many duties which belong vnto God, yet this quality of <hi>feare</hi> includes them all; and many duties and offices to be done to man, yet this quality of <hi>regard</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends them all; now becauſe he wanted <hi>feare</hi> he wanted all the reſt, and ſo performed no duty vnto God, and becauſe he wanted <hi>regard,</hi> he wanted all the reſt, and ſo performed no good office vnto man: He was voyd of all grace, either to God or man.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how this Iudge is deciphered, and his Armes blaſoned in the Text, according to the words: But now let vs goe to the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was a Iudge,</hi> and firſt of all, let it not ſeeme ſtrange that Chriſt in this <hi>Parable,</hi> compares Almighty God, to this <hi>vnrighteous Iudge:</hi> for hee doth not compare things that are equall, but the leſſe with the greater: Thus; if a man get his right by importunity, at the hands of a moſt <hi>vnrighteous Iudge,;</hi> how much more ſhall the continuall prayers of the godly preſſing the eares of God preuaile with God. Beſides, we know in Scripture that ſometimes compariſons to good purpoſe, are taken from things that are euill: as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22662:4"/>of Chriſt to iudgement, is compared to the comming of a <hi>Theefe in the night,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. Neither doe Parables ſerue to proue, or approue euery thing by their circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for then ſhould diuers foule and groſſe abſurdities ariſe. As in that of the <hi>Rich man</hi> and <hi>Lazarus, Luke</hi> 16. For thence it ſhould appeare, that the ſoules of the damned in hell ſhould haue materiall and fleſhy tongues; as alſo that in hell there ſhould be water to coole, both which are ridiculous. Againe, that the damned ghoſts ſhould be zealous of Gods glory, in the furtherance of mans ſaluation vpon the earth: For <hi>Abraham</hi> is entreated by the Rich man, that <hi>Lazarus</hi> might be ſent to <hi>admoniſh</hi> his fiue brethren, and to worke their conuerſion, that ſo they might avoid thoſe inſufferable torments. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> therefore giueth a good rule whereby to interpret Parables; <hi>not according to the letter, but according to the ſence.</hi> The ſcope &amp; intent of Parables, is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be regarded. As in that of the Rich man and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the intent is to ſet forth the ſeuerall and diuers eſtates of two men in this life, and their ſeuerall and diuers eſtates in the life to come, by reciprocall proportion. So this Parable holds not in all, but in the ſcope and intent wherevnto it was vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as before is declared.</p>
            <p>But for the <hi>Perſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">There was a Iudge.</note> whoſe office was a Iudge; <hi>There was a Iudge,</hi> and thus far I like it very well; yea, &amp; that he ſhould be in a <hi>City</hi> too, for an eminent place is fit for an eminent perſon.</p>
            <p>The Office of a Iudge is of great Honour, of long Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, of great Neceſſity. Firſt of Honour, becauſe they are Gods deputies, ordained of him, vpon earth to be next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him: <hi>Iudges and Magiſtrates ſhalt thou make in all thy Cities throughout thy Tribes,</hi> ſayth God to <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 16.18. <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that be, are ordained of God, Rom.</hi> 13.2. God aſſumeth vnto himſelfe the title of a Iudge, elſe would not <hi>Abraham</hi> haue beene ſo bold, <hi>Shall not the Iudge of the whole world doe right? Gen.</hi> 18.25. God ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on their bench and iudgeth amongſt them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1. Their honour muſt needs be great when he layes vpon them his owne name, <hi>God ſtandeth in the aſſembly of gods:</hi> and hee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22662:4"/>auoucheth it with his owne mouth, <hi>Ego dixi, dii eſtis; I haue ſayd ye are gods. Moſes</hi> is called <hi>Pharaohs</hi> god: and <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> called his Biſhops gods. Chriſt expounding that place of the Pſalme before rehearſed, ſaith, <hi>Hee called them gods to whom the word of God was, Iohn</hi> 10.34. which is not to bee vnderſtood of the generall doctrine, directed to all the ſons of God, <hi>ſed de ſpeciali dominandi mandato,</hi> as <hi>Caluin</hi> well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth it, of the ſpeciall charge of gouernment, whether it be Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall. And they are ſo called, <hi>Ne quid admittant quod eos dedeceat, qui loco Dei ſedent:</hi> that they might doe nothing iniuriouſly, baſely, or otherwiſe vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming, becauſe they ſit in his place, &amp; are gods vnder God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their Antiquity appeares partly by that which I haue ſaid before, they are as ancient as <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was both a Temporall Iudge and an Eccleſiaſticall, and ſo continued, till after he reſigned his Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction to <hi>Aaron.</hi> And after the death of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ioſuah,</hi> the Gouernors ouer Iſrael for many yeares together, were called <hi>Iudges,</hi> of whom <hi>Samuel</hi> was the laſt. The <hi>Ephori</hi> among the Lacedemonians, and the <hi>Areopagitae</hi> among the Athenians, were Iudges, and theſe long ſince determined weighty matters, concerning their gouernment, and puniſhed offenders.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Neceſſity of their office appeares many wayes, but eſpecially two: Firſt, in that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>They are the Miniſters of God for our wealth, Rom.</hi> 13.4. For where good Iudges and Magiſtrates are, there commonly good cauſes thriue and proſper, Godly lawes are conſcionably adminiſtred, the glory of God is aduanced, and the kingdome of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged: and ſuch haue ſpeciall right and due intereſt in their places. Secondly, neceſſary, for they are the <hi>Miniſters of God to take vengeance on them that doe euill,</hi> to bridle and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the corruptions and miſdemeanours of wicked men, to puniſh the looſeneſſe and exorbitancy of their liues, to ſuppreſſe their inſolencies, root vp their vices, and righten the wrongs of the oppreſſed. And there are three ſeuerall <hi>ſpecies</hi> or kinds of puniſhment, which they may inflict, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſets them downe: Either, firſt, to puniſh them in their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22662:5"/>bodies; or ſecondly, to puniſh them in their purſes; or thirdly, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to put to open ſhame.</p>
            <p>Now as God placeth them in their ſeats of Iuſtice, which are called the <hi>Seats of the Mighty,</hi> but not that they ſhould be ouer mighty in their ſeats, obſtreperous and comberſome, and alloweth them alſo Princely or prieſtly Roabes, <hi>ad glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam &amp; ornatum, Exod.</hi> 28.2. not ſo much for their owne carcaſſes, which are but earthly and mortall, as for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their places. As <hi>Seneca</hi> wrote to the wife of <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperour, <hi>Indue te delicatè, non propter te, ſed propter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem imperij:</hi> So God alſo hath ordained and required that they ſhould be adorned, not onely <hi>regijs veſtibus, ſed &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gijs &amp; egregijs virtutibus,</hi> which according to <hi>Iethro's</hi> aduice to <hi>Moſes</hi> are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be men of <hi>courage,</hi> to goe through their affaires with a wiſe and a ſtout reſolution. For I doe not thinke that <hi>Iethro's</hi> meaning was onely that they ſhould be <hi>pollentes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> but <hi>valentes ingenio,</hi> induſtrious, and able to expedite cauſes with good dexterity and wit; and ſo they ſhall be ſure to doe nothing, either <hi>incautè</hi> or <hi>inconſultè,</hi> raſhly, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They muſt <hi>feare God</hi> which is both the <hi>beginning of wiſedome,</hi> and the foundation of all vertue, and they are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Magiſtrates and Iudges, in whom this <hi>feare of God</hi> is wanting.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They muſt be men of <hi>Truth,</hi> not onely <hi>ſpeculatiuè,</hi> in knowing, diſcerning, and iudging, but alſo <hi>practicè,</hi> in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing a right iudgement, and obſeruing the rules of truth. For there is as well <hi>veritas vitae,</hi> the truth of life, when the conuerſation is framed according to the rule of truth; as <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas iuſtitiae,</hi> the truth of Iuſtice, in diſcerning right from wrong.</p>
            <p n="4">4 They muſt hate <hi>Couetouſnes:</hi> For that will quench and deſtroy all good vertues in them. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, it is the <hi>roote of all euill;</hi> as that which giues ſap and nouriſhment to all other ſinne. And where this growes to the height, it beares downe all: yea, this deteſtable and accurſed hunger of gold,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22662:5"/>what doth it not effect? nay, whom doth it not affect? The Poets faine of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> that ſhe commits adultery in chaines; but I am out of doubt, much wrong and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may Iudges doe in their places, who are eyther drawne on, or faſt bound with the golden chaine of Couetouſneſſe. Hence it is that they are long-handed after bribes, which Father <hi>Latimer</hi> cals a Princely kinde of Theenery. Sure, it was not for nothing, that as in old time, the Iudges of <hi>Thebes</hi> were painted or carued out <hi>ſitting,</hi> which argued a ſetled moderation, a treatable, deliberate, gentle proceeding; (for they ſhould not be like <hi>euill Spirits</hi> in their places, onely to vexe and torment:) and with <hi>eyes ſhut,</hi> or turned another way; as hauing no reſpect of perſons: So alſo were they portrayed <hi>without hands, vt à donis eſſent alieni,</hi> that they ſhould not reach after gifts and bribes, <hi>which blinde the eyes of the wiſe, and peruert the wayes of the iuſt.</hi> They muſt haue an honeſt and conſcionable intent to aduance the glory of God, and puniſh vice; and not be <hi>Aucupes Nummorum,</hi> courſing vp and downe in their Circuits and Iuriſdictions abirding after money: yet is this the maine diſeaſe of many, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Other vertues are required in a Iudge,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as wiſedome, &amp; vnderſtanding, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.15. but neyther theſe, nor any other before rehearſed, were in this Iudge: yet was it very fit they ſhould, for he was in a place of eminencie, he was in a <hi>Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a certaine Citie.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">In a certaine Citie.</note> Which is not onely to be taken for the fabricke, poſition, ſcituation, habitation, charters, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, all which make a Citie: but for the people and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. When newes came to <hi>Shilo</hi> that <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> were ſlaine, and the Arke of God taken, <hi>All the Citie,</hi> that is, all the inhabitants of the Citie, <hi>cryed out.</hi> Nay thirdly, a <hi>Citie</hi> alſo is taken for the whole body of a Country, as <hi>Marlorate</hi> vpon that place of the Pſalme, <hi>The Lord keepeth the Citie,</hi> he ſpeaketh there ſaith he, <hi>de Reipub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licae ſtatu &amp; politia,</hi> of the policy and ſtate of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Take the word <hi>Citie</hi> here, in any of theſe ſences, I am ſure it noteth thus much, that <hi>Cities</hi> are the ſpecialleſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22662:6"/>and moſt remarkeable places of a Country, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly containe vnder their iuriſdiction the Villages there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about. 2. They are the ſeats of great men, and of great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and men in them preferred to office and dignity, are the more eminent and conſpicuous. 3. They are the ciuileſt places, and fulleſt of knowledge and good manners. 4. which is not the leaſt, they are the moſt religious too. Now all theſe, makes againſt this Iudge, that hauing his reſidency and abode in a <hi>City,</hi> a place of <hi>eminencie,</hi> a place of <hi>ciuility</hi> and good manners a <hi>religious</hi> place, and where perhaps, he needed haue gone but a few ſteps to his Temple to haue worſhipped; yet that hee ſhould be ſo <hi>irreligious</hi> as not to <hi>feare God;</hi> or haue ſo little <hi>ciuility</hi> or good <hi>manners,</hi> as not to <hi>regard man.</hi> And ſo I come to his <hi>Qualities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Ex parte Dei. He feared not God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I goe further, I pray doe but note. This is a very ſtrange Teſtimony that Chriſt here giues of a Iudge, <hi>There was a Iudge in a certaine City who feared not God, neither regarded man.</hi> I ſhould rather haue thought it had beene a good Teſtimony, to haue beene giuen of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer</hi> or a <hi>Drunkard.</hi> And if Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>There was an Vſurer in a certaine City,</hi> or, <hi>There was a Drunkard in a certaine City,</hi> and either of theſe, <hi>neither fearing God, or regarding man,</hi> this had beene ſomewhat; nay, very probable. But to ſpeake thus of a Iudge, who beares an office of Honour, of Antiquity, of Neceſſity: one who ſits in the roome of God, to execute his Iudgements; <hi>horreſco referens,</hi> I tremble to ſpeake it. O thou bleſſed Sonne of God, the eternall Wiſedome of thy Father I that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Heauen-dropping dew,</hi> whoſe words are as Aples of gold with pictures of ſiluer, inwardly rich, inwardly precious, euermore to ſingular and ſpeciall purpoſe, whatſoeuer thou diddeſt, whatſoeuer thou ſpakeſt was for our inſtruction. For ſurely, hereby he would teach vs, that 1. whatſoeuer their perſons or their places be, if they be wicked and doe wickedly, let it not bee concealed, but declared, ſpoken of, and ſpoken of ſo, that poſterity may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22662:6"/>take notice of it. For to this end are the ſinnes of good men and bad men too in Scripture recorded and related. Let their faces be made aſhamed, who knoweth, whether the diuulging and publiſhing of their faults may bring them to repentance, as being humbled and ſtricken through with ſorrow and contrition. Excellent is the ſpeach of that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man, <hi>Sireprche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di fers aegrè, reprehende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da ne feceris;</hi> If they thinke much to heare of their wickedneſſe, let them abhorre to doe it. Yea let others heare and feare by their example. Why ſhould the Scholler be ſpared for hope of his learning, or the Gentleman for his birth, or the Doctor for his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or the Iudge for his authority, if they be ſhameleſſe or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant? And if we may not ſpare our <hi>right eye</hi> or our <hi>right hand,</hi> if they be cauſes of offence; why ſhould we then ſpare the offences of others, who ſhould be <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, order, and ſettle vs in a good courſe, by their diſcipline and example. I confeſſe greatneſſe thinkes it ſelfe much priuiledged; and the ſinne of a great man, like mount Sinai may not be touched. Yet are the Prophets commanded to <hi>cry aloud and not to ſpare;</hi> and the Miniſter of God he muſt be <hi>veronenſis,</hi> and not <hi>placentinus.</hi> As <hi>Gedeons</hi> Souldiours had in one hand a Lampe, in another hand a Trumpet: ſo wee muſt haue a comfortable ſhine to enlighten ſome, a ſhrill and warlike ſound to rouze vp others. Yea let euery good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter know, that he is as the Arke, wherein was as well the <hi>rod of Correction,</hi> as the <hi>Manna of Conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſpeakes this to let vs ſee, that ſometimes wicked and vile men, men voyd of Gods feare and of all goodneſſe, are promoted to places of office and dignity. And this is as great a plague as may be; diſhonorable to God, diſgracefull to the place, impatible and grieuous vnto the people. What a ſtorme of dreadfull imprecations doth the Prophet call for from heauen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. like a raine almoſt of fire and brimſtone, a very tempeſt of euils, vpon wife, children, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, goods, or what elſe were more deare, ſmiting all theſe as with the ſtings of Scorpions? The firſt of them all that leadeth the daunce, as <hi>Iudas</hi> lead the curſed band of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22662:7"/>Souldiers, is, <hi>Set thou a wicked man to be ruler ouer them.</hi> I thinke there could not be a wickeder then <hi>Hee</hi> this, for firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He feared not God.]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who feared not God.</note> And here I pray conſider, firſt, the <hi>Quality, feare;</hi> which in Scripture is taken many wayes, eſpecially two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the worſhip and ſeruice of God, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. <hi>I will teach you the feare of the Lord,</hi> that is, I will inſtruct you rightly concerning the true worſhip of God. And <hi>Eſay.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Their feare</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>towards me was taught by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of men:</hi> that is, their religion, and manner of worſhip was learned by mans doctrine, and not by my Word. And our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. interpreteth this place after the ſame manner, <hi>In vaine doe they worſhip me, teaching for doctrine the precepts of men.</hi> The oath that <hi>Iacob</hi> tooke <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.42. was by the <hi>feare of his father Iſaak.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, I ſweare by that God whom my father worſhips. For God is ſometime called by names <hi>effectiuè,</hi> as when he is called Our health, our ſtrength, our ſaluation. Sometime <hi>obiectiuè,</hi> as when he is called Our ioy, our hope, our feare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the obiect of all theſe, and the ſcope and end of all our worſhip and ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Feare</hi> is taken for an awfull dread and reuerence of God, whereby wee make conſcience of all our actions and words, as ſtanding in his preſence. <hi>Elias</hi> thought that <hi>Ahab</hi> would haue ſuppoſed him but an idle fellow, when hee told him, that neyther dewe nor raine ſhould fall in Iſraell of three yeares, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. and therefore addes, that <hi>hee ſtood in the preſence of God,</hi> whom becauſe hee <hi>feared</hi> with an aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full regard, it behooued him to make conſcience of what he ſpake. It was the ſpeech of the Theefe, vnto his fellow Theefe vpon the Croſſe, <hi>Feareſt thou not God, ſeeing thou art in the ſame condemnation?</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, Doeſt thou not conſider the place, and caſe, wherein thou art? Standeſt thou in no <hi>feare</hi> of him who now taketh vengeance on thee for thy forepaſſed iniquities? And doeſt thou ſtill perſiſt to reuile, and raile vpon this righteous man? <hi>Feareſt thou not God?</hi> This kinde of <hi>Feare</hi> is expreſſed by <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 4.4.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22662:7"/>
               <hi>Stand in awe.</hi> Nay, take <hi>Feare</hi> in this place which way you will, this Iudge <hi>feared not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, conſider the obiect of this <hi>feare. God;</hi> And him either as he is abſolute and entire of himſelfe, his moſt liuely and perfect eſſence; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Ens ille; Ille qui eſſentiam ſuam a ſeipſo habet;</hi> the perfection of whoſe nature, is the abſolute con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution thereof, as wholly compleate within it ſelfe: Or, ſecondly, conſider him in his Attributes and properties, wherein he is, the ſame with himſelfe; For, <hi>Quicquid eſt in Deo, Deus eſt,</hi> according to the Schoolemens rule: the Lord of Hoſts ſtrong and mighty great and glorious, the ſtrength of Iſrael, yea of the whole world; cloathed with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Maieſty as with a garment: The glory of his Face farre more glorious then all the glorious lights of Heauen: the whole beauty of Nature, but a ſparke of that beauty wherewith he is beautified. Eſpecially conſider him in his Iuſtice; a dreadfull God, a God of vengeance, powring out his wrath like fire, and reſeruing it for thouſands: He loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vpon the Angels and they tremble; He faceth the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and they melt; toucheth the mountaines and they ſmoake; ſhaketh the Earth, and her pillers fayle; diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Seas, drieth vp the riuers, rendeth the Rocks in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der like a thred of flaxe. <hi>Baſhan is waſted, and Carmel, and the flowre of Libanon is waſted.</hi> The Lords way is in the whirlewind and in the ſtorme, and the cloudes are the duſt of his feet. <hi>Thou, thou O God art to be feared, for who can ſtand before thee when thou art angry?</hi> Smoake goes out of his noſtrils, and a flame of fire out of his mouth, coales are kindled thereat. <hi>Moſes</hi> could not endure the ſight of his preſence, for <hi>hee was afraid to looke vpon God:</hi> nor the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple endure to heare him, <hi>O let not God ſpeak vnto vs, leſt we dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or in the ſecond place. Take God in the ſweeteſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of his Nature. Loue, mercy, ſauing-health, light of his countenance, patience, long-ſufferance, liberality, his ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableſt diſpoſition, fauour, grace, aboundance of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, gratiouſly interpreting our offences, ſetting by his Iuſtice, as the ſteward in the Goſpell ſet by his accounts,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22662:8"/>and when the debt is an hundred, ſets downe but fifty; Nay vtterly cancelling our indictments, blotting <hi>all our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe out his remembrance:</hi> I ſay, take God either ſimply as he is of himſelfe; or in regard of his properties, and thoſe the moſt eminent and conſpicuous; as he <hi>iuſt,</hi> and a God of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, or as he <hi>mercifull</hi> and a God of patience; All is one with this Troyan horſe, this Cyclops that warreth againſt heauen, and careth neither for <hi>Iupiter</hi> nor his Thunderbolts, reſpecting not his dreadfulleſt lookes, no, nor yet his ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and pleaſanteſt nature of mercy, I ſay all is one; <hi>Hee feared not God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue had too much of him in this.
<note place="margin">Nor regarded Man.</note> But now wee are come to the ſecond quality, <hi>He regarded not man:</hi> and yet ſurely <hi>Man</hi> in many reſpects deſerues ſome regard. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of nature, the ſweeteſt, compleateſt modell of all his workes; the very <hi>centrum</hi> and <hi>epitome</hi> of all his creatures. He, who rightly deſerueth to be ſtiled <hi>OMNIS CRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ATVRA,</hi> The Philoſopher ſaith that <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>miraculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium miraculum maximum:</hi> a miracle of miracles. And <hi>Dauid</hi> acknowledgeth himſelfe, and in himſelfe all others, to be <hi>maruelouſly made, Pſal.</hi> 139.</p>
            <p>The Stoicks made him to conſiſt of ſoule and body as we doe. But the <hi>Platonicks</hi> who were a diuiner ſect, made man a diuiner thing; and ſaid, that hee was wholy ſoule or ſpirit, onely compact and tyed vp together, with certaine fleſhly and earthly ligaments. Indeed <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>hee was lower then God,</hi> and but a little; <hi>a little lower then God, Pſa.</hi> 8.3. a very remarkable creature ſure, and deſeruing ſome <hi>regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, God at his creation ſpake not of him, as of other creatures, <hi>fiat lux,</hi> let there be light, and ſo of the reſt, but, <hi>faciamus hominem,</hi> let vs make man. By which manner of ſpeech, God intended, not any aſſiſtance, either of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Angels, to be co-workers with him in mans crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or that he ſpake in the plurall number for ſtate, after the manner of the Princes of the earth. But God almighty part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreſeeing there would be heretiques afterward, denying the Trinity, but eſpecially, for the honour of this his <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22662:8"/>piece,</hi> or workemanſhip, he ſpeakes of the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as if the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt were in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation together about the creation of <hi>Man:</hi> A creature therefore of ſome <hi>regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, hee was made into the Image of God; which though it be diuerſly interpreted, and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath many conceipts, much adoe about it; placing this Image ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in one thing, and ſometime in another: and yet, that good Father I am ſure, not ignorant of that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. where we may ſee how we are to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this Image of God in man. I ſay euen this redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth much to his honour and <hi>regard,</hi> that by the right of his creation, his very nature was conformable to the nature of God; Holy as he is holy, righteous as he is righteous; I ſay for the Quality, though not for the Equality, as hauing the ſame holineſſe in nature, though not in the ſame meaſure. This Image was broken in pieces in the fall, and yet is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred and renewed againe, through Chriſt (who is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the couenant of Grace,) in all thoſe who haue put off the old man, and put on the new: and ſome parcells or remnants of thoſe broken peeces yet remaine (as the ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ruines of a demoliſhed pallace,) euen in thoſe, that are vncalled; as certaine notions in the minde concerning God, of the power of God, of good and euill, of reward and puniſhment, which haue no other vſe, but to leaue men without excuſe in the day of vengeance.</p>
            <p>Againe, almighty God made many creatures in the world beſides, as the Behemoth by Land, and that Prince of the Ocean, the Leuiathan by Sea. Both which wee know <hi>Iob</hi> notably diſcribeth. Of the latter hee ſaith, <hi>Iob</hi> 41. <hi>I will not keepe ſilence of his power, of his parts, and of his comely propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The Lord God made many others, diuerſe in nature, different in kind, infinite in number, &amp; hath giuen to euery one a ſeuerall life, and ſeuerall degrees of life, from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to the Emmet. But he made them not ſo much for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as for man, who is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the very <hi>end</hi> and perfection of all theſe. To this purpoſe <hi>Chriſtoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh ſweetly,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22662:9"/>
               <hi>Animalia fecit Deus propter hominem, hominem vero propter ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum;</hi> He made all the creatures for man, but he made man for himſelfe onely. And he addeth, that if God ſo gratiouſly miniſtreth vnto the creatures for mans ſake, how much more doth he miniſter vnto man, for his owne ſake? And therefore a creature of ſome <hi>regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet further, there is a ſpeciall relation, alliance, affinity betwixt God and man, as if he were <hi>bone of his bone: For we are alſo of his generation, Act.</hi> 17.21. It may be, ſaith <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon that place, that <hi>Aratus</hi> the Poet thought there were ſome parcells of the diuinitie in mens mindes, as the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> did ſay, that the ſoules of men were of the nature of God. But the meaning is, that man by the excellency of his nature, reſembles ſome diuine thing, and proceedes as a ſpeciall Beame, from that heauenly and diuine nature; a creature ſure of ſome <hi>regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay further yet, God hath made man <hi>animalſociale,</hi> a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable creature, and hath giuen him a face of a very gratious and amiable aſpect, a hand to congratulate, an arme to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, a boſome to endeare, the very ſeat of kindneſſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency and loue; reaſon alſo, and ſpeech, two ſingular and rare prerogatiues, beyond all earthly creatures. All, all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of humanity, as he ſaid in the comedy, <hi>Homoſum, humani nihil à me alienum puto:</hi> I am a man, and I imagine no part of humanity, impertinent vnto mee. In that Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no doubt, it is very probable, as in others of the like, were great ſtore of fooles and vulgar perſons, yet did this ſpeech ſo naturally touch the affections of them all, that Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 52.</note> They all gaue an admirable applauſe vnto it. By all which it appeares, that man is a creature of ſome <hi>regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet this <hi>Animal beſtiale, Animal obſcoenum et olens,</hi> as one ſpake of the Scarab flie; this Heterogenian, whelpe of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other kind, a very Miſanthropos, an hater of his owne kind, a Tymon, demon, I ſay not the ſonne of <hi>Belial,</hi> but <hi>Belial</hi> himſelfe: he hath no more <hi>regard</hi> or humanity in him, then if the Rockes had fathered him, the ſhe-Wolfe had brought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22662:9"/>him forth, or that hee had drawne his milke from the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons in the wilderneſſe. <hi>He regarded not man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The word here in the originall vſed for <hi>regard,</hi> ſignifies more then <hi>curare,</hi> or, <hi>curam habere,</hi> and yet that argues a manifeſtation of it in outward action; but <hi>pudore,</hi> or <hi>verecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia afficere,</hi> or <hi>reuereri,</hi> an inward affection of <hi>reuerence:</hi> and ſo by conſequence, an open, reſpectiue, gratious deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and cariage towards man. Here alſo is an <hi>Heteroſis,</hi> or an <hi>Enallage numeri,</hi> which is the ſurrogation of the ſingular number for the plurall, vſuall in the Scripture. Therefore to expreſſe it rightly <hi>Beza</hi> doth well tranſlate it, <hi>nec quenquam reuerebatur,</hi> as who ſhould ſay, It was not ſo much this man or that man, but all were alike to him, <hi>He reuerenced not any, He regarded not man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay to this vnciuile Iudge? wee know the Gentiles (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of the men of Athens,) <hi>were in all things too ſuperſtitious.</hi> Some of them worſhipped the Sunne at his riſing vp, and regarded not his going downe. Others worſhipped him at his going downe, but reſpected not his riſing vp. If this <hi>Iudex bellicoſus,</hi> Theanthropomaſtix, If he had <hi>feared God,</hi> though hee had not <hi>regarded man,</hi> or if hee had <hi>regarded man,</hi> though hee had not <hi>feared God,</hi> this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of him had not beene ſo foule. But hee was <hi>Totus in maligno poſitus:</hi> Hee was wicked <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>à fronte et à tergo.</hi> For he neither <hi>feared God,</hi> who was before him, nor <hi>regarded man,</hi> who came behind him, wicked <hi>à dextris et à ſiniſtris,</hi> He neither <hi>feared God,</hi> who was at his right hand, nor <hi>regarded man,</hi> who was at his left: wicked, <hi>ſurſum et deorſum.</hi> He neither <hi>feared God,</hi> who was aboue, nor <hi>regarded man,</hi> who was below. <hi>He feared not God, he regarded not man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray tell me, what thinke yee, might become of him. For my part, I thinke long to be rid of him, and ſo happly did that iuriſdiction likewiſe, where hee had to doe. And bleſſed, euer bleſſed be he, whoſoeuer he were, that gaue the change; which was as gratious and welcome no doubt as a ſhowre of the latter rayne. His people might haue ſaid of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22662:10"/>him, as they ſpake in the Pſalme; <hi>O when ſhall he dye, and his Name periſh?</hi> What became of him I know not; but ſure I am, he deſerued no better doome then that of Laodicea, <hi>to be ſpued out of Gods mouth:</hi> or elſe that which God ſpake and threatned to <hi>Iehoiakim, Ier.</hi> 22.19. <hi>They ſhould not lament for him,</hi> or ſay, <hi>ah my Lord; alas, thy glory;</hi> but as a dead <hi>Aſſe</hi> drawne and throwne without the gates of that <hi>City:</hi> though formerly he had ſate on his Bench, as an <hi>Ipſe inter primos,</hi> — now it might be ſpoken of him, as it was ſaid of <hi>Labienus,</hi>
               <q>— Nunc transfuga vilis.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> writes of the Crocodile,
<note place="margin">Nat. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>lib.</hi> 8.25. that being well ſtuft with his prey, and wallowing with his paunch vpon the bankes of <hi>Nilus,</hi> he falls into a ſleepe, and in his ſleepe he gapes; meane while the bird <hi>Trochylus</hi> pickes his teeth, and clenſeth them one after another, and goes his way; But then comes the Ichneumon, as perilous a Serpent in Egypt as ſomething elſe in England, and gets through into his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, teares them a pieces, and ſo he dies. It is many times the iuſt iudgement of God vpon ſuch men, who hauing greedy appetites, which are neuer of the beſt diſgeſtion, that being well ſtuft with riches and wealth, either by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of their offices, or bribery of their places, fortifying themſelues againſt Heauen, wallowing in their abundance, to be ſecure: yet God meetes with them at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that though their inmoſt conſciences be cauterized and ſeared vp, yet ſomething, <hi>ſub nomine pacis,</hi> workes their ſhame and diſhonour. What ſhould God elſe meane, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.2. when he threatens the wicked Iudges of Samaria, that he would take them away with <hi>fiſhookes,</hi> but that they ſhould ſwallow downe ſomewhat into their throat, that ſhould turne to their bane?</p>
            <p>I haue now done;
<note place="margin">Application.</note> And haue beene all this time in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; I haue gone through the Text, and haue ſhewed you one poynt after another: <hi>Adhuc eſt paruulum,</hi> There is yet a little thing behind, ſomething to be further ſpoken by way of Application. And as Chriſt in the former Chapter giues an <hi>Item</hi> for <hi>Lots</hi> wife, <hi>remember Lots wife;</hi> ſo ſay I, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22662:10"/>this vnrighteous Iudge.</hi> And though we might ſpeake of him, as God ſpake of <hi>Amelech, Deleatur memoria Amelech ſub coelo:</hi> Let the memory of <hi>Amelech</hi> be blotted out from vnder Heauen; And though vnworthy he is, <hi>that any menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him ſhould come within my lips;</hi> yet a little remembrance will not doe amiſſe, for that, he hath layd himſelfe forth as an example.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, a Iudge he was;
<note place="margin">A Iudge.</note> it is Gods ordinance to ſet ſome aboue in place to rule, and others beneath in places to obey, and as <hi>Iuuenal</hi> cals <hi>Eagles</hi> the ſeruants of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſo ſuch are the ſeruants and Miniſters of God, by an honorable prerogatiue, in being his deputies and vicegerents: And ſurely, had this man honored God in his place, God would haue honoured him againe: For, <hi>they that honour mee, I will honour.</hi> And let them further know that whom hee aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to ſuch offices and dignities, hee expects they ſhould <hi>walke worthy</hi> of their places, and not be <hi>carried away,</hi> with ſundry luſts of intemperancy, iniuſtice, couetouſneſſe, and the like, to the diſhonour of God, and the irreuerence of their owne perſons. It is very incongruous and vnbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that he who by reaſon of his calling, comes neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, there is none further from him.</p>
            <p>Neither is this onely for the Iudge, but for all ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of what ranke ſoeuer they be; Eſpecially Paſtors and Miniſters of the Church, (who haue an eminency of place, ouer the ſoules of men,) that they adorne the Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus, with ſoundneſſe of Doctrine and integrity of life. The walls of Iericho were beaten downe, but by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes then the Trumpets of the Prieſts; and the ſtrong holds of Satan are onely battered downe, with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſound teachers. Their good example alſo of life, is of great force, <hi>Nuga in ſecularibus, in ſacerdotibus blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> That which is but a trifle, and as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of nothing in a Lay-man, is as ill as blaſphemy, or the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt almoſt, in a Church-man, and therefore not to demeane our ſelues, as one ſpake of the Monkes of old time;</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22662:11"/>
            <q>
               <l>— Qui praeter amictum</l>
               <l>Nil aliud verae Relligionis habent.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Cut but the hayre from the eye-brow, ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and how disfigured will the face looke, there is but a ſmall thing taken from the body, but a great matter from the beauty. Honor God therefore in thy place, by thy doctrine and conuerſation, and whatſoeuer thy former frailties and eſcapes haue beene, yet recompence thy forepaſſed ſinne, with a ſanctified obedience, And let me adde this more, if thou haſt gifts of learning and knowledge, let them not be ſmothered vp and kept as concealed land, but returne them to the right owner, and improue thy Talent thou art truſted with to thy maſters aduantage; it will be hereafter thine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ioy and comfort, though nothing in the world com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee beſide. And herein are many of vs faulty, who are lazy and negligent, making our Sermons as miſers doe their feaſts, rare and ſeldome, but then farced and furniſhed with ſuch varieties, as tend to ſurfet rather then to profit. The flocke of Chriſt ſhould be <hi>fed</hi> and <hi>fed</hi> and <hi>fed, Iohn</hi> 21. which argues a continuall feeding, yet ſome of vs take liberty to do it when we liſt; yea, it is almoſt a miracle to heare ſome of vs ſpeake: I would be more earneſt in this, but our Lay men doe befriend vs, and are quit with vs in this kind, for wee cannot be ſo dumbe as they are deafe; deafe at any thing that ſhould profit them in the matter of Saluation, and as deafe at any thing that makes for our profit. In either of theſe like <hi>Dauids</hi> Adder, who <hi>refuſed to heare the voice of the Charmer, charme he neuer ſo wiſely.</hi> But howſoeuer, let as well the Paſtor as the Iudge make conſcience of his duty. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſat ille qui diſpenſat.</hi> He that ſets vs to our taske, giues vs our pay; when our chiefe Shepheard ſhall appeare, we ſhall be recompenſed for all our paines, <hi>Cùm ad opus piger es, quare ad mercedem feſtinas?</hi> How ſhall we thinke either to haue ioy or peace of conſcience in this life, or eternall happineſſe in the life to come, when we are ſlothfull to the worke? What a bleſſed voice ſhall that bee, when wee heare that bleſſed voice in the Goſpell, <hi>Well done thou good and faithfull ſeruant:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22662:11"/>thou haſt beene faithfull in a little,</hi> not a little <hi>faithfull,</hi> no, that will not ſerue the turne; but <hi>faithfull in a little,</hi> that is, little was thy learning or knowledge, to that which others haue, in the deepe things of God; few thy gifts and ornaments, little perhaps, thy cure and charge, but becauſe thou wert faithfull in a little, <hi>I will make thee ruler ouer much, enter thou into thy maſters ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I may not omit this alſo,
<note place="margin">There was.</note> that Chriſt here ſayth not There is, but <hi>There was,</hi> which implies, that whatſoeuer the pride and inſolency of this man was, either not to <hi>feare God,</hi> or <hi>diſ-regard man;</hi> yet hee was either taken away by death, for euill things haue their periods as well as good; or which is liklieſt, ſecluded from his place, through ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident diſaſterous, and ſo for an earthly puniſhment, became as currant and conuerſant a by-word for matter of reproach as once was <hi>Daedalꝰ in omni fabula.</hi> Were he excoriate as once a Iudge in Athens, and his skinne hung vp in <hi>terrorem:</hi> Or were he expelled the City where he liued, and the gates cloſed vpon him: Or were he ſhut out of the campe and company of the Hoſt, becauſe <hi>he was vncleane,</hi> I cannot ſay, onely Chriſt ſaith here, <hi>there was,</hi> there is not. I would euer haue a Iudge to remember three things. Firſt, that they are <hi>men,</hi> as himſelfe is ouer whom hee hath his authority. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, theſe men he muſt gouerne according to a preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>law,</hi> and not according to the lawleſſe affections of his owne heart. Thirdly, he ſhall not <hi>alwayes</hi> gouerne, but as others haue giuen place to him, ſo muſt he to others. In the meane time therefore whilſt he is in place, to demeane him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the <hi>feare of God,</hi> and with due <hi>regard to man:</hi> In theſe ſtriuing to excell all that went before, and to be a preſident to as many as ſhall ſucceed; wiſdome, knowledge, grauity, zeale, diligence, <hi>vprightneſſe of heart,</hi> in his proceedings, are notable ornaments in a Iudge, eſpecially to ſanctifie his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and his place, by frequent inuocation and prayer vnto God. To haue a <hi>pure and vncorrupt heart,</hi> this, this will make him <hi>a ſtarre at the right hand of God;</hi> and that he ſhine out amongſt others of his rancke, with that tranſparency and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22662:12"/>beauty, like <hi>Mercury</hi> himſelfe betwixt thoſe radiant Orbes of <hi>Venus</hi> and the Moone.</p>
            <p>Nor yet is this to be ouerpaſſed,
<note place="margin">In a certaine City.</note> that Chriſt here ſaith hee was in <hi>a City.</hi> It was no maruaile ſure, his manners were ſo good I thinke the baſeſt village in all the Iſle had been good enough. It was the manner of the <hi>Cretians</hi> to boaſt of the number of their <hi>Cities,</hi> I am ſure they needed not ſo haue done, of the goodneſſe of their Iudges. <hi>He</hi> this, <hi>was in a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> And not vnlike neither, but hee had ingroſſed for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a faire houſe with gardens and orchyards; but I doubt he kept his Gates as faſt barred, as that purple Churle in the Goſpel; and that he was none of the beſt to the poore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Text ſaith, he <hi>regarded not man.</hi> But this I am ſure of, that in this <hi>City</hi> where he dwelt, lay his authority and Iuriſdiction, becauſe in the next verſe, the widow that came to him for Iuſtice, dwelt in the ſame <hi>City.</hi> A great diſhonor was he no doubt vnto it. For in ſuch populous places as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are, where men conuerſe within a wall, as ſeuerall and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe almoſt in their conditions and manners, as in their trades and callings, the decent, orderly and examplary life of the Iudge and Magiſtrate who liues amongſt them, is of great conſequence. For it ſtands as a looking glaſſe before the peoples eyes. And his good example is of better perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion then the power of his place: Elſe ſuch <hi>Cities</hi> are as ill incombred, as that of <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> of which <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> the <hi>Sicilian</hi> writes, that they nouriſhed that great bird <hi>Ibis</hi> to deuoure the garbage and offall of their <hi>City,</hi> and to cleanſe their ſtreets, but he left of his owne filth and beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more noyſome behind him. So ſuch a one, by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of his calling is very profitable, to purge and cleanſe the places where his power lieth, from enormities and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, which if his diſcipline were not, would grow noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and abhorring; yet when it comes to this, that hee growes irregular and inordinate, through his luſts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancies; and hath not <hi>ventrem bene moratum,</hi> a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly belly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 132.</note> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaketh, ſurely he leaues more ſtench and filth behind him, through his bad example, then the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22662:12"/>good which he pretends to doe, by vertue of his place, can recompence or repaire. Hence is it requiſite that great care be had of the choiſe of ſuch. That face is but vncomly, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the eyes are bleare, and full of humours; ſo it is but a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and disfigured gouernment, where men of authority are aſperſed and beſmeared with the groſſe and odious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, either of Luxury or iniuſtice: Yea, to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 109.30. <hi>With great thankes,</hi> and to prayſe him <hi>amongſt the multitude,</hi> when he diſplaceth ſuch, and placeth better in their roomes, for hee euermore <hi>ſtandeth at the right hand of the poore, to ſaue his ſoule from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Iudges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, concerning his Qualities,
<note place="margin">Who neither feared God.</note> he is here noted with a blacke cole, that he <hi>feared not God.</hi> But wee that expect to receiue the <hi>white ſtone,</hi> and in that ſtone <hi>a new name</hi> written, which no man knowes, but hee that receiues it, in what cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or place ſoeuer we be, let vs practiſe the contrary. For, firſt in a Iudge, the want of this <hi>feare</hi> is a wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauſhment; it will make him as proud as <hi>Herod,</hi> as cruell as <hi>Nero,</hi> as prophane as <hi>Iulian,</hi> as vniuſt as <hi>Pilate,</hi> as ſenſuall and beaſtly as <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> as couetous, dogged, churliſh as <hi>Nabal,</hi> and perhaps as drunke too; as diſſolute as <hi>Baltaſar,</hi> ſwilling and carouſing wine before thouſands, prauncing ouer his cups, and calling to the ſeruitour, for the fulleſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and pureſt liquor, Ho!</p>
            <q>
               <l>Miniſter veteris puer Falerni,</l>
               <l>Ingere mi Calices alacriores.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the meane time, regardleſſe of the iudgements of God. The want of this <hi>feare</hi> in a Paſter or Miniſter, will make him as worldly as <hi>Demas,</hi> as ambitious as <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> as carnall as an Epicure, as licentious as a Libertine, as falſe hearted to his Cure, as <hi>Iudas</hi> was to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The want of this <hi>feare</hi> in a Lay-man, will make him run into any diſorder, euen to the ſhipwrack of his conſcience: and here are many of you preſent, this day, who I feare, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22662:13"/>
               <hi>His feare</hi> poſſeſſe you, will launch out into a fearefull deepe; rather then you will duely and truely preſent accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your oath; daubing ouer faults, defaults, yea the groſſe ſinnes of others, with the vntempered morter of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and conniuency: <hi>Theſe things are in the eares of the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> when men ſhall come in open Court, preſent their bodies before the Iudge, their bodies and ſoules before God, who ſhall be their lateſt and fearefulleſt Iudge; and in the preſence of them both, and all the bleſſed Angels of Heauen, take a ſolemne oath, binding ouer themſelues actually to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall vengeance, if they fayle in their legall charge, and yet account no more of the oath thus miniſtred, then if the wind had blowne vpon them, whereas there goeth a ſecret and vnſeene vertue out of the oath, as there did out of Chriſts veſture, either to iuſtifie or condemne them; I ſay againe, <hi>Theſe things are in the eares</hi> (yea and in the eyes too) <hi>of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Generally in all men the want of this <hi>feare,</hi> is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all euill, Holy and faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſhifting for himſelfe before King <hi>Abimilech, Gen.</hi> 20.11. for ſaying that <hi>Sarah</hi> was his ſiſter, whereas indeed ſhee was his wife, and being demanded the cauſe why he did ſo, anſwerd modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and religiouſly for himſelfe, <hi>I thought thus, ſurely the feare of God was not in this place, therefore they will ſlay mee for my wiues ſake;</hi> giuing vs to vnderſtand, that where the <hi>feare</hi> of God is not, no conſcience is made of any ſinne whatſoeuer. Hence ariſeth all thoſe groſſe and abhominable ſinnes of murders, adulteries, drunkenneſſe, prophaning of the Lords Sabbaths, blaſphemous oathes, deceitfull bargaines, accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vſuries, wherewith the land groneth, and I know not what! And let men be reproued, and theſe ſinnes ſmitten with therod of our lips, like gunpowder (being ſcalt) they fly backe in our faces, and offer to ouer-maſter vs. As inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are they as <hi>Plinies</hi> Beares; <hi>vix vulneribus excitari poſſunt;</hi> they ſtir not with many ſtabs, or like that Fencer at the ganies of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> whom <hi>Aulus Gellius</hi> mentioneth, that when his wounds were gaſhed and launced by Surgeons, vſed to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22662:13"/>laugh at them: Or like thoſe <hi>Celtes</hi> that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeakes of, who were ſo mad and without paſſion, that neither by thunders nor earthquakes, or the noyſe of fearefull inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they would euer be moued, or remoued: Or like thoſe old Italians, of whom I haue read, that in the foreſt tempeſts of Thunders and lightnings, they would ſhoot off their greateſt ordinance, and ring out their deepeſt bells, that the noyſe of the one, might mitigate, the horrour of the other; So inſenſible are men, and without remorſe, that they will audaciouſly conteſt, confront, oppoſe, and improue their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible wickedneſſe to the height, againſt our loud and powerfull reprehenſions; their hearts as fat Brawne, their ſoules impenetrable, euen like Iericho, ſhut vp and incloſed. Hence is the cauſe of all, with this <hi>Anteſignanus Nequitiae,</hi> this <hi>Theomachus;</hi> they <hi>feare not God,</hi> or as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>men haue forgotten the feare of the Almighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, this Iudge is here taxed with inciuility,
<note place="margin">Nor regarded man.</note> or want of good manners, he <hi>regarded not man:</hi> I wonder then if there were any man <hi>regarded him,</hi> or gaue him a good word, any good report. <hi>A good name,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, is better then a precious ointment;</hi> yet with many, a precious ointment is better then a good name: I haue ſeene men outwardly ſmell of ſweet perfumes, but inwardly they haue had an ill ſauour of all vices: yet men in high place, aboue all things, are to reſpect this; carefully to auoyd infamy, and ill report, which quickly ſpreades out, and inlargeth it ſelfe, as we know in a troubled water, one circle begets another, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and therefore the Poet ſaid well,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fama malum, quo non aliud velocius vllum:</l>
               <l>Mobilitate viget, vireſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> acquirit eundo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Few in high place but much regard this; howſoeuer this ſlow bellied, ſwilbellied Cretian, wallowing in his ſtinke and ſinke of iniquity, as <hi>Lot</hi> in his drunkenneſſe, commits abhominable inceſt, with his two daughters, the elder and the yonger, <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>ſhame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22662:14"/>
            <p>Secondly, He offended in the Negatiue, but let vs care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully practiſe the affirmatiue, namely to reuerence and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard man.</hi> Yea I ſay <hi>man, cuiuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conditionis,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſpake to that Romane <hi>Pollio,</hi> of what condition ſoeuer he be. Though hee bee much thine inferiour, hee is made into the ſame Image with thy ſelfe, endued with the ſame ſhape, and liueth vnder the ſame gouernment and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of the Creator, and (as thou oughteſt in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to thinke,) within the compaſſe of Gods Election. <hi>Hee is a man,</hi> Giue him a ciuill reuerence and <hi>regard.</hi> The whole Law is reduced into two maine parts, The loue of GOD, and the Loue of our Neighbour; the one begets the other: and hee that loues not his brother whom he hath ſeene, can neuer loue God whom he hath not ſeene, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.20.</p>
            <p>This loue ſhewes it ſelfe amongſt other things by a ciuill and courteous behauiour towards man: <hi>Peter</hi> amongſt other duties, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. requires this, <hi>Be courteous to all men:</hi> &amp; in the 3. of <hi>Titus</hi> 2. <hi>Put them in remembrance that they be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> How courteous and reſpectfull were the ſonnes of <hi>Heth</hi> to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 23.6. being in a ſtrange country, and put to it for a buriall place for his wife: <hi>In the chiefeſt of our Sepulchers bury thy dead?</hi> And becauſe they would ſhew their <hi>regard</hi> the more, they adde words enough, and words good enough: <hi>None of vs ſhall forbid thee his Sepulcher, but thou maieſt bury thy dead therein.</hi> It is the commendation of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon, Iudges</hi> 8.3. <hi>He ſpake courteouſly to the men of Ephraim.</hi> But it muſt not be ſuch courteſie as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.3. <hi>To ſpeake friendly to their neighbours, but imagine miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe in their hearts:</hi> To be <hi>foris Cato,</hi> and <hi>intus Nero;</hi> of an outward plauſible countenance, and of inward malitious intendments. It was forbidden in the Law to weare linſey woolſey; and I am ſure they breake the Law of God, who weare garments wouen of ſimplicitie and ſubtilty together. Once men ſaluted hand in hand, ſaith one, but now wee caſt arme in arme: But an handfull of that old friendſhip is worth a whole arme full of this new courteſie. Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22662:14"/>wee muſt be courteous, and giue <hi>regard</hi> euen to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men: So <hi>Paul</hi> behaued himſelfe before <hi>Feſtus,</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him <hi>noble.</hi> Wee muſt reſpect them not as they are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but as they are men; loue their perſons, loath their vices. A wicked man may be of our acquaintance, and wee may vſe him courteouſly, yet let him neuer be our compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to be vſed entirely. Be at peace with all men, but at warre with their vices. Againe, there be, who will <hi>regard</hi> men, and vſe them regardfully, but no further then they ſerue their turne; as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ſent his wife to <hi>Ahijah</hi> the Prophet, and bade her carry him a preſent of bread, and wafers, and honey, which <hi>Ieroboam</hi> would haue ſcorned to doe, but that he thought the Prophet could benefit him by his aduice. And ſuch is the condition of many in this age, who will <hi>regard</hi> a Miniſter, when they ſee they muſt make vſe of him, eyther to be viſited in their ſickneſſe, or that they might be graced with a Sermon at the buriall of their friends, or at their marriage, or vpon ſome other high occaſion; otherwiſe we may goe long enough ere wee be <hi>regarded</hi> or lookt after.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer, this Iudge was wonderfull faulty, hee gaue no <hi>regard,</hi> whereas our duty is to <hi>regard man,</hi> though he be a ſtranger, though he be an inferiour. What a ſpeciall fauour was that which God did to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to call him by his proper name. The Angell ſaluted <hi>Gedeon, The Lord bee with thee thou valiant man.</hi> But if he bee ſet in place aboue thee, if a Father, if a Maſter, if a Magiſtrate, or inſtead of any of theſe; giue him that <hi>reuerence</hi> and <hi>regard</hi> that is due vnto him. Which condemnes the ſawcy malepartneſſe of children, ſeruants, people; who will diſhonor their Parents, diſpiſe their Maſters, and conteſt with their Rulers and men in authority, and braue them to their face: Both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> complaine of theſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Iude</hi> 8. I wiſh they were not ſo ordinary as they are.</p>
            <p>Yet further, if he be thy ſpirituall Father, thy Paſtor and Miniſter, giue vnto him a <hi>double honour,</hi> as well of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as of maintenance, <hi>Regard</hi> him as a man, but much
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22662:15"/>more as a man of God, ſet ouer to inſtruct thee, and to guide thy ſoule aright to the Kingdome of glory. How faulty are many of our ill nurtured Laity in this kind; who looke ouer vs as high as Caedars; ſupercilious and lofty like the Iewes? They tooke no knowledge of Chriſt, that he was their King, or of his Royall deſcent, or that hee was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of the world, and ſhould dye for the ſaluation of man: of all this they tooke no notice. They knew him for a Carpenter, and a Carpenters ſonne, and ſuch to be his brothers, and ſuch to be his ſiſters. So we, we ſhall bee readily knowne by the meanneſſe of our birth and kindred, the leanneſſe of meanes and liuing, the poore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſtipends, or what elſe may adde to our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; but not of the dignitie and excellencie of our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, maintenance for our ſeruice, countenance to our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; like flyes they leaue the ſound parts, to ſucke at a botch; <hi>Let a man ſo eſteeme of vs as the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Obey them that haue the ouerſight of you, for they watch for your ſoules, as they which muſt giue an account. I admoniſh that you haue them in ſingular loue for their workes ſake.</hi> Carnall men and the common ſort, when they heare vs thus to ſpeake, they thinke we preach to extoll our ſelues, and to gaine reputation. No, we ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi> in the humility of our ſoules, <hi>Non nobis Domine, non nobis, Not vnto vs O Lord, not vnto vs,</hi> but vnto thy name giue the prayſe: If we haue <hi>regard</hi> and eſteeme at the hands of men, we haue but our due. But (meane while) let God haue the Honour, by your obedience to his truth, loue to his word, by your care and conſcience to practiſe thoſe doctrines which faithfully we teach: this ſhall be our ioy, our crowne, our recompence ſufficient; otherwiſe, none of his glory ſhall cleaue to our fingers.</p>
            <p>Finally,
<note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> All of vs, whether wee be in place to rule, or in place to obey; in place to teach, or in place to heare; let vs in the reuerence and <hi>feare</hi> of GOD, ſo carry and demeane our ſelues to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man, That God euen our owne God may giue vs his bleſſing,</hi> that hee may bleſſe and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22662:15"/>ſanctifie our gouernment, ſanctifie our obedience, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our teaching, ſanctifie our hearing, and all good duties of our life beſide. I will conclude therefore with that prayer of the Apoſtle: <hi>Now the God of peace ſanctifie you throughout, and I pray God that all our hearts and ſoules may be kept blameleſſe vntill the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
